<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Pat Browne</title>
    <link>https://patbrowne.me/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Pat Browne</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://patbrowne.me/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Right to left computability</title>
      <link>https://patbrowne.me/posts/rtolcompute/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://patbrowne.me/posts/rtolcompute/</guid>
      <description>Manipulating bits Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been going through Hacker&amp;rsquo;s Delight. It is a joy to become a &amp;ldquo;bit-twiddler&amp;rdquo; and explore some of the counter intuitive properties of using bit wise operations in places you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect them.
Chapter 2 focuses on &amp;ldquo;Basics&amp;rdquo;, and covers bit manipulation tricks that perform specific operations. It assumes a 32-bit machine (and word size), with signed values represented in two&amp;rsquo;s complement form. 1 Some tricks presented include:
 $x \; \&amp;amp; \; (x - 1)$: turn off the rightmost bit in a word $x \; \&amp;amp; \; (x + 1)$: turn off the trailing 1&amp;rsquo;s in a word $\neg x \; \&amp;amp; \; (x + 1)$: create a word with a single 1-bit at the position of the rightmost 0-bit $x \; \&amp;amp; \; (-x)$: isolate the rightmost 1-bit, produce 0 if none  Note that these hacks are much more useful than they might appear. The first trick can be used to great effect to count set bits and calculate powers of two, as demonstrated in Brian Kernighan&amp;rsquo;s algorithm2:
unsigned int v; // count the number of bits set in v unsigned int c; // c accumulates the total bits set in v for (c = 0; v; c++) { v &amp;amp;= v - 1; // clear the least significant bit set } These bit wise operations allow for implementations of functions that are branch-free and do not require shift instructions, saving valuable CPU cycles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding learning with errors</title>
      <link>https://patbrowne.me/posts/lwe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://patbrowne.me/posts/lwe/</guid>
      <description>Cryptographic protocols that perform computations on encrypted data without decrypting it are known as homomorphic encryption. Fully homomorphic encryption (FHE) protocols, systems which support arbitrary computations, often rely on different primitives than conventional cryptography systems. Most FHE systems in practice used lattice-based cryptography, relying on a computational hardness assumption known as the learning with errors (LWE) problem.
Cryptograhy relies on assumptions Prior to the 20th century, cryptography did not rely on a formalized system of provable security. Rather, one set of people (cryptographers) would come up with clever ciphers, and another set of people (cryptanalysts) would attempt to break those ciphers. Encryption schemes such as the Caesar cipher, the Vingenère cipher, the Enigma, and other systems were not formally proven secure by cryptographers. Rather, they relied on obfuscation and statistical properties that made deciphering messages fairly difficult. However, each one of these systems had some sort of flaw that cryptanalysts were able to exploit to decipher encrypted messages. 1
Modern cryptography, starting in the 1970s and 80s, changed the way we define security to be about adversarial capabilities rather than strategies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-life examples of Markov chains</title>
      <link>https://patbrowne.me/posts/markov/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://patbrowne.me/posts/markov/</guid>
      <description>One of the classes that I&amp;rsquo;m taking this semester is on stochastic processes. Stochastic processes are sequences of random variables $X_1, X_2, &amp;hellip;, X_n$, where $n$ represents a specific moment in time.1 The first topic we&amp;rsquo;ve focused on this semester has been Markov chains, specific stochastic models that only depend on the current state. They are unique in that future events are only affected by where you currently are, not where you have been in the past. Markov chains arise from the law of total probability, which is a way to express the probability of an event as the sum of many other probabilities. In general, when dealing with a stochastic process, you have to condition the probability of an event on all previous events before, as they all have some effect on whether or not you reach that state. Mathematically, this can be expressed as
$$P[X_{n+1} = m \mid X_0 = i, X_1 = j, &amp;hellip;, X_n = k]$$
However, with Markov chains, we only need to focus on the most recent event.
$$P[X_{n+1} = m \mid X_n = k]$$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why do commands require tabs in a Makefile?</title>
      <link>https://patbrowne.me/posts/makefile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://patbrowne.me/posts/makefile/</guid>
      <description>When I was first learning how to write a Makefile to compile a C program, one thing that stuck me (and almost everyone who encounters it) as odd was the requirement that each command line start with a tab character (&#39;\t&#39;). Makefiles are used to automate repetitive tasks (such as recompiling a C/C++ program), and have a unique syntax. They are made up of rules, which consist of a &amp;ldquo;target&amp;rdquo;, a list of &amp;ldquo;dependencies&amp;rdquo;, and a series of &amp;ldquo;commands&amp;rdquo;. They look like this:
target: dependencies command For example, suppose I want to automate two different tasks: recompiling my program after editing some of the source code, and deleting all non-source files after editing them. I could write a Makefile that looks like this:
.PHONY: clean myprogram: myprogram.c gcc myprogram.c -o myprogram clean: rm *.o *~ myprogram The .PHONY makes sure that when I run the shell command make clean, I don&amp;rsquo;t create a file named clean. Instead, I run the command underneath, which removes the files I don&amp;rsquo;t want in my directory. The other rule has a target filename myprogram, which requires a file named myprogram.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
