<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Electronics on Pat Browne</title>
    <link>https://patbrowne.com/tags/electronics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Electronics on Pat Browne</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://patbrowne.com/tags/electronics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building circuits with the 74HC595 (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://patbrowne.com/posts/shiftreg1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patbrowne.com/posts/shiftreg1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the first of two posts about shift registers. This post focuses on some
history behind integrated circuits, how the 74HC595 works, and how to build
simple circuits with it. The second post will explore more complex circuits, as
well as how shift registers are used today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img
src=&#34;https://patbrowne.com/img/shiftreg/sn74hc595n-image.jpg&#34;
alt=&#34;Image of an SN74HC595N integrated circuit&#34; width=&#34;35%&#34;&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Many general-purpose electronics kits include a few integrated circuits (ICs) in
addition to jumper wires, resistors, capacitors, and other electronic circuit
components. A common IC included in kits is the 74HC595N, often one manufactured
by Texas Instruments (SN74HC595N). After receiving a few of these in various
electronics kits, I built several circuits with this shift register to
understand how it works.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-on-integrated-circuits&#34;&gt;Background on integrated circuits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circuits are made up of electrical components, such as resistors, capacitors,
transistors, and diodes. While all circuits can be made up of these components,
it is often necessary to combine several parts together into a single component,
where the parts are closer together, smaller, and merged into a single building
block. These circuits are typically etched onto a semiconductor material, such
as silicon, and are known as &lt;strong&gt;integrated circuits&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;ICs&lt;/strong&gt; for short.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
