<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>complexity on Pat Browne</title>
    <link>https://patbrowne.me/tags/complexity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in complexity on Pat Browne</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://patbrowne.me/tags/complexity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding learning with errors</title>
      <link>https://patbrowne.me/posts/lwe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://patbrowne.me/posts/lwe/</guid>
      <description>Cryptographic protocols that perform computations on encrypted data without decrypting it are known as homomorphic encryption. Fully homomorphic encryption (FHE) protocols, systems which support arbitrary computations, often rely on different primitives than conventional cryptography systems. Most FHE systems in practice used lattice-based cryptography, relying on a computational hardness assumption known as the learning with errors (LWE) problem.
Cryptograhy relies on assumptions Prior to the 20th century, cryptography did not rely on a formalized system of provable security. Rather, one set of people (cryptographers) would come up with clever ciphers, and another set of people (cryptanalysts) would attempt to break those ciphers. Encryption schemes such as the Caesar cipher, the Vingenère cipher, the Enigma, and other systems were not formally proven secure by cryptographers. Rather, they relied on obfuscation and statistical properties that made deciphering messages fairly difficult. However, each one of these systems had some sort of flaw that cryptanalysts were able to exploit to decipher encrypted messages. 1
Modern cryptography, starting in the 1970s and 80s, changed the way we define security to be about adversarial capabilities rather than strategies.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
